Preliminary Guide to the Sidney Weintraub Papers, 1938-1984 and undated RL.01360
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sidney Weintraub papers
1938-1984 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Weintraub, Sidney, 1914-1983
RL.01360
16 Linear Feet
Professor and economist specializing in Post Keynesian economic theory. These files document much of Sidney Weintraub's career as an economist; material dates from the early part of his professional career, 1938, until his death in 1983. Also included is a later accession with personal correspondence between him and his family.
Approximately 18,170 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sidney Weintraub Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1984, in the 1990s and in 2009.
Biographical Note
Sidney Weintraub (1914-1983) was an American economist and a professor who specialized in the post-Keynesian school of economics. He was best known for his proposal to use the federal income tax to discourage wage and price inflation in a tax-based incomes policy (TIP). Raised in New York, Weintraub studied at the London School of Economics before being forced to return to the United States at the outbreak of World War II. He earned his Ph.D. from New York University in 1941, and began teaching economics at St. John's University following the war. He joined the Wharton School at the University of Pennsylvania in 1950, where he remained for the rest of his career. Weintraub also founded and co-edited the Journal of Post Keynesian Economics.
Weintraub married Sheila Ellen Weintraub and had two sons, E. Roy and A. Neil Weintraub. E. Roy Weintraub is an economics professor at Duke University.
This note includes information gathered from: Saxon, Wolfgang, Sidney Weintraub Dies at 69; An Economist and Professor, New York Times, 21 June 1983.
Collection Overview
These files document much of Sidney Weintraub's career as an economist; material dates from the early part of his professional career, 1938, until his death in 1983; it also includes some post-humous material from 1984. The collection is arranged into seven series: Correspondence, Subject Files, Writings, Miscellany, Clippings, Photographs, and Printed Material. There are also descriptions of additions and oversize materials following the main collection description. Weintraub is best known for his work on inflation, wages and prices, unemployment, economic growth, and post-Keynesian monetary theory. Other significant topics in the papers include Weintraub's work with the U.S. government on economic policies, and his travels in England during and after World War II.
The Correspondence Series contains letters between 1939 and 1983. Weintraub, who did much of his own typing, scrupulously preserved carbon-copies of the letters that he sent to others which are included in the files, along with original letters sent to him by others. The bulk of the correspondence is dated between 1970 and 1983, a time when Weintraub was at the University of Pennsylvania and Waterloo in Canada (see Accession 2009-0178 for earlier correspondence). Weintraub regularly corresponded with a number of economists, including: Joan Robinson, Martin Brofenbrenner, Nicholas Kaldor, Abba Lerner, Henry Wallich, John K. Galbraith, Roy Harrod, Francis Seton, E. Roy Weintraub, Alice Vandermeulen, G.C. Harcourt, and many others. He also corresponded with many non-economists, including: Senators Barry Goldwater, William Proxmire, Gary Hart, and Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey. An addition from 2009 consists largely of Weintraub's personal correspondence to his wife, Sheila Ellen Weintraub, during World War II and his post-war travels. It has been added to the end of the collection.
One problem arises when using the material in the Correspondence Series of Weintraub's papers, since this section is indexed and stored by year or portion of a year and not by author or receiver of the correspondence. Therefore, for the years 1970 through 1983, it is difficult to find particular letters for particular individuals if the date for the correspondence is unknown. For earlier years this is not such a problem given the smaller number of letters in the files prior to 1970.
The Subject Files Series is the largest, comprising nearly one-fourth of the initial collection. The material grows out of research undertaken by Weintraub primarily during the period 1970 to 1983 when he was attempting to influence government policy by promoting the merits of a Taxed-Based Incomes Policy (TIP). Of particular interest here is the early work on the publication of Capitalism's Inflation and Unemployment Crisis. Also of interest is the work that Weintraub did for the Canadian Institute for Economic Policy. In this series the material concerning the founding of the Journal of Post Keynesian Economics is included. This includes correspondence with co-editor Paul Davidson and publisher M.E. Sharpe, Inc. There is also some preliminary correspondence having to do with the publication and writing of Keynes and the Monetarists. These files contain material dealing with Weintraub's extensive national and international lecturing tours, with materials from trips to Europe, Asia, Puerto Rico, and much of the United States. Finally, material on the writing of Modern Economic Thought, editorials for the New York Times, and the Puerto Rico Economic Quarterly is included in this category.
The Writings Series includes work both by Weintraub himself and by others, both published and unpublished. Of Weintraub's own work, there are early versions and drafts of works later published. For example, one finds early work on the published piece Keynes and the Monetarists and Other Essays, by Sidney Weintraub along with Hamid Habibagahi, Henry Wallich, and E. Roy Weintraub (1973). Also included is some early work on the 1981 book Our Stagflation Malaise. Several unpublished drafts can also be found here including portions of the uncompleted work Economic Thought: 1945-1965, which also had the title Recent Developments in Economic Theory. Other uncompleted works are Economics of Capitalism and Keynesian Evolution: A Theory of Employment, Growth, Income Distribution, Inflation and Money, with Policy Implications. This rather lengthy title was the second revised title of a proposed book that assessed both the microeconomic and macroeconomic components of Post Keynesian monetary theory. Finally in this section are the completed, yet unpublished, works Pricing Interstate Telephone Services: Some Aspects of FCC Regulations of the Bell System Pricing Policies and The Theory of the Structure of Interest Rates.
The Miscellany Series contains other writings by Weintraub at different times in his professional career. Of particular interest is Weintraub's testimony to various congressional committees and federal regulatory bodies. Also included are Weintraub's handwritten notes on several of the graduate and undergraduate classes that he taught, including The History of Economic Thought, Recent Developments of Economic Theory, Theories of Business Cycles, Theory of Value and Distribution, an Introduction to Mathematical Economics, Price and Distribution Theory, Seminar in Selected Problems of Economic Theory, Public Finance and Modern Economic Theory, Keynesian Economics, Topics in Macroeconomics, and partial notes on other courses and subjects as well.
The Clippings Series contains newspaper and magazine articles by Weintraub or about his economic theories. They are written pieces from the popular press. Included in the clippings are letters to the editor from publications throughout the United States and Canada. For the most part, these articles by Weintraub or mentioning Weintraub deal with aspects of Taxed-Based Incomes Policy (TIP). Though not all of these clippings related to economics, the majority of them do.
Both the Photographs and the Printed Material series of the files are limited. The former contains only a few black and white publicity pictures from one or more of Weintraub's speaking tours. The latter houses only a few journal reprints. Of special interest in the volumes series is an unpublished manuscript sent to Henry Wallich at the time of their first collaboration on Taxed-Based Incomes Policy. It outlines, in detail, Weintraub's ideas on the subject from Professor Wallich.
The group of materials added to the main collection at a later date deals with research that Weintraub was considering at the time of his death. This includes an early draft of a book, titled Post Keynesian Evolution. In these files are also condolence letters received by Mrs. Weintraub at the time of her husband's death, along with various obituaries and eulogies.
Accession (2009-0178) (1.2 lin. ft.; 900 items; dated 1937-1971) consists largely of Weintraub's personal correspondence to his wife, Sheila Ellen Weintraub, during World War II and his post-war travels. Other correspondents include his brother and his son. These letters offer excellent insight into Weintraub's activities during the war, as well as descriptions of London and India in the pre-war and post-war period. This accession has been added to the end of the collection; see below for box numbers.
Collection Arrangement
The collection has been loosely arranged according to the series listed above, which were established by the Manuscript Department when the collection was acquired. There are additions whose descriptions have been appended to the main collection. Accession (2009-0178) has been grouped chronologically by year, but has not been interfiled with the Correspondence Series.
Inflation (Finance); India, 1940-1950; London (England), 1940-1950; Keynesian economics; Unemployment -- Effect of inflation on; Photographs; World War, 1939-1945; Wage-price policy; Economists -- Correspondence; Economics -- History -- 20th century; Economists -- United States; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Weintraub, Sidney, 1914-1983; Weintraub, Sidney, 1914-1983; Vandermeulen, Alice John, 1918-; Weintraub, E. Roy; Bronfenbrenner, Martin, 1914-1997; United States Information Service; Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1908-2006
- Correspondence Series, 1939-1983 and undated, 6 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence series contains letters between 1939 and 1983. Weintraub, who did much of his own typing, scrupulously preserved carbon-copies of the letters that he sent to others which are included in the files, along with original letters sent to him by others. The bulk of the correspondence is dated between 1970 and 1983, a time when Weintraub was at the University of Pennsylvania and Waterloo in Canada (see Accession 2009-0178 for earlier correspondence). Weintraub regularly corresponded with a number of economists, including: Joan Robinson, Martin Brofenbrenner, Nicholas Kaldor, Abba Lerner, Henry Wallich, John K. Galbraith, Roy Harrod, Francis Seton, E. Roy Weintraub, Alice Vandermeulen, G.C. Harcourt, and many others. He also corresponded with many non-economists, including: Senators Barry Goldwater, William Proxmire, Gary Hart, and Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey.
  - 1939-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - 1973-1976 (Box 3)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - 1979-1981 (Box 5)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 6)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 6)
- Subject Files Series, 8 boxes
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Co. (Box 6)
    Primarily correspondence, 1974-1977, concerning the publication of Capitalism's Inflation and Unemployment Crisis.
  - The American Academy of Political and Social Science, Sept. 1973 issue of Annals (Box 6)
    Includes correspondence (1972-1973), papers and miscellaneous essays that were published in this volume, of which Weintraub was special editor, on the subject of income inequality.
  - Canada--Economic Policy (Box 6)
  - Canadian Institute for Economic Policy (Box 7)
  - Data for Incomes Policy for Full Employment Without Inflation (See also: Volumes Series) (Box 7)
  - Economic Council of Canada (Box 7)
    Includes correspondence (1976), paper (New Avenues to Explore) by Weintraub, and papers which document Weintraub's travel expenses and other costs incidental to writing Incomes Policy for Full Employment Without Inflation.
  - Centre International des Sciences Mecaniques: Round Table (Box 7)
    Held in 1980 in Udine, Italy. Its topic was A Critical Appraisal of the Present State of Economics. This conference was a precursor to the Centro Di Studi Economici Avanzati.
  - Centro Di Studi Economici Avanzati (Box 7)
  - The First International Summer School of Economics and the First Conference on Economics (Box 7)
    Both were held in 1981 in Trieste, Italy. The conference topic was Distribution, Effective Demand, and International Economic Development.
  - The Second International Summer School of Economics and the Second Conference on Economics (Box 7)
    Both were held in 1982; the summer school was in Trieste, Italy, and the conference was in Udine. The conference topic was Theories of Accumulation and the Control of the Economy.
  - The Third International Summer School of Economics and the Third Conference on Economics (Box 7)
    Both were held in 1983; the summer school was in Trieste, Italy, and the conference was in Udine. The topic of the conference was The Economic Dynamics of Resources, Technology, and Employment--Theories and Policies for Open Economies.
  - Chilton Book Co. and Greenwood Press (Box 7)
    Correspondence, 1971-1974, concerning the following books: Intermediate Price Theory, Keynesian Theory of Employment Growth, Some Aspects of Wage Theory and Policy, A General Theory of the Price Level, Output, Income Distribution and Economic Growth, Classical Keynesianism, Monetary Theory and the Price Level, and An Approach to the Theory of Income Distribution.
  - Collier-MacMillan Canada, Ltd. (Box 7)
    Correspondence, 1971, concerning the essay An Incomes Policy for a Market Economy, which is included in this folder, and its publication in Canadian Perspectives in Economics.
  - Derivation of K (Box 7)
  - Income Inequality (Box 7)
    Correspondence, 1974, in an unsuccessful attempt to have this work published.
  - Incomes Policy (Box 8)
    Correspondence, 1970-1971, clippings, and miscellaneous papers.
  - ITE Imperial Corporation (Philadelphia, Pa.) (Box 8)
  - Journal of Post-Keynesian Economics (Box 8)
    Correspondence with M.E. Sharpe, Inc., 1976-1981. Also includes correspondence with Paul and Louise Davidson, 1977-1983.
  - Editorial correspondence, 1978-1981 (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - General correspondence, 1977-1983 (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Keynes and the Monetarists (Box 9)
    Primarily correspondence, 1971-1977, with University of Pennsylvania Press and Rutgers University Press.
  - Lecture Engagements (Box 9)
  - Babson College, March 1981 (Babson Park, Md.) (Box 9)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of Philadelphia, Jan. 1972 (Box 9)
  - Middlebury College, April 1979 (Box 9)
  - Society for Advancement of Management, April 1973 (Box 9)
  - Southern Economic Association Meeting, Nov. 1971 (Urbana, Ill.) (Box 9)
  - Speakers Bureau of Philadelphia, Aug. 1971 (Box 9)
  - United States Information Service (USIS) (Box 9)
  - Australia, Malaysia, New Zealand, July-Aug. 1974 (Box 9)
  - Canada, March 1975 (Box 9)
  - Europe, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
  - Europe, 1971-1972; 1975-1976; 1982 (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Europe and the Middle East, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Asia, India, and Australia, 1971 and 1979 (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - United States Office of Personnel Management, Government Affairs Institute, Sept. 1981 (Box 10)
  - University of Arizona, Feb. 1978 (Box 10)
  - University of Pennsylvania Club of Baltimore, Dec. 1972 (Box 10)
  - University of Puerto Rico, Nov. 1974 (Box 10)
  - University of Tampa, 1974 (Box 10)
  - Washington University and the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis, Sept. 1971 and Nov. 1978 (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Wharton Graduate School Alumni of Chicago, May 1972 (Box 10)
  - Modern Economic Thought correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 10)
  - National Science Foundation Project (Box 11)
    Concerns the proposal Market Oriented Incomes Policies, which was first submitted in 1972 and re-submitted in 1977.
  - New York Times correspondence, 1971-1981 (Box 11)
  - Puerto Rico Economic Quarterly correspondence and essays, 1979-1981 (Box 11)
  - Research Institute in Contemporary Economic Studies correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 11)
  - University of the South correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 11)
  - University of Waterloo, 1969-1971 (4 folders) (Box 11)
    Graduate Program of Economics, sabbatical information, staff information, and miscellany.
  - Western Lumber Manufacturers, 1959 (Box 12)
  - Williams College correspondence, 1981 (Box 12)
- Writings Series, 7 boxes
  - Articles by Weintraub (filed alphabetically by title) (Box 12)
    - Comments on works by others (Box 12)
    - A-R (Box 12)
    - S-Z (Box 13)
  - Articles by Others (filed alphabetically by author)
    - A-R (Box 13)
    - S-Z (Box 14)
  - Books: Published Works (drafts) by Weintraub
    - Keynes and the Monetarists and Other Essays (Box 14)
      Authored by Sidney Weintraub along with Hamid Habibagahi, Henry Wallich, and E. Roy Weintraub, 1973.
    - Our Stagflation Malaise, 1981 (Box 14)
  - Books: Unpublished Works (drafts) by Weintraub (Box 15)
    - Economic Thought: 1945-1965 (Box 15)
      The earlier title for this work, Recent Developments in Economic Theory, has been crossed out.
    - Economics of Capitalism (Box 15)
      This work is subdivided into two divisions: book I is entitled, The Theory of Affluent Welfare Capitalism, and book II, The Consumption Sector: Basic Needs and Amenities Plus Frills, Fads, and Flourishes. This work was not completed.
    - Keynesian Evolution: A Theory of Employment, Growth, Income Distribution, Inflation and Money, with Policy Implications (Box 15)
      Other titles include: The Keynesian Evolution: Towards Money Micro-Macro Market Models, and Some Post Keynesian Evolution in Micro-Macro Money Theory. There are at least four different versions of the Table of Contents. This work was not completed.
    - Pricing Interstate Telephone Services: Some Aspects of FCC Regulation of the Bell System Pricing Policies (Box 16)
    - The Theory of the Structure of Interest Rates (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous Writings
    - Capacity as an Economic Concept, Part I (Box 16)
    - Early Economic Thought, Arthur Munroe, ed., 1951 (Box 16)
    - Employment Growth and Income Distribution (preface to Japanese edition) (Box 17)
    - A General Theory of the Price Level, Output, Income Distribution and Economic Growth (preface to the Japanese edition) (Box 17)
    - Impediments to Entry (Box 17)
      Chapter 19 of unknown work.
    - The Pricing of Telephone Service: Testimony of Sidney Weintraub (Box 17)
    - Selections from the history of economic thought (Box 17)
      Abridgements of works by the following authors: Adam Smith, David Ricardo, John Stuart Mill, and Karl Marx.
    - Statement to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs (Box 17)
      Testimony given to the U.S. Senate Committee on May 23, 1978.
    - Statement to the Joint Economic Committee (Box 17)
      Testimony given on Feb. 23, 1979.
    - Testimony to the Federal Communications Committee (Box 17)
      Statement concerning the possible earnings of AT&T in the future.
    - Unknown titles (Box 17)
- Miscellany Series, 4 boxes
  - General (Box 17)
    See also OV:VI:15.
  - Notes (Box 17)
    Notes relating to the following courses taught by Weintraub: History of Economic Thought, Recent Developments of Economic Theory, Theories of Business Cycles, Theory of Value and Distribution, Introduction to Mathematical Economics, Price and Distribution Theory, Seminar in Selected Problems of Economic Theory, Public Finance and Modern Economic Theory, Keynesian Economics, Topics in Macro-Economics, and perhaps other courses and subjects as well. Many of the folders contain notes on books.
  - Notes (Box 18-20)
  - Notes, Economic Thought, 1945-1965 (Box 18-20)
  - Papers, chapter 1, 3, and 4 (Box 18-20)
- Clippings Series, 1 box
  - Articles by Weintraub, including letters to the editor (Box 20)
    - Clippings, 1951-1983 (Box 20)
    - The Evening Bulletin, 1971-1975 (Box 20)
  - Clippings about Weintraub or his economic theories, 1950-1983 (Box 20)
    Articles and letters to the editor which, for the most part, mention Weintraub and deal with his ideas on economics, especially Tax-Based Incomes Policy (TIP).
  - General clippings, 1954-1983 (Box 20)
- Photographs Series, 1 folder
  - Chiefly publicity shots (Box 22)
- Printed Material Series, 2 boxes
  - Articles by Weintraub (Box 21)
  - Miscellany (Box 21)
  - Miscellany (Box 22)
  - Volumes (Box 22)
- Addition (1984 November), 2 boxes
  - Correspondence, 1981-1984 (Box 23)
  - Legal and financial papers, primarily book contracts (Box 23)
  - Articles by Weintraub (Box 23)
  - Articles by others (Box 23)
  - Post Keynesian Evolution (Box 23)
    Along with drafts to portions of this book are notes and correspondence relating to its development and completion by Paul Davidson and Neil Owen after Weintraub's death. Also includes two floppy discs containing the early chapters of the book.
  - Post Keynesian Evolution (Box 24)
  - Clippings, including obituaries (Box 24)
- Addition (93-161), 1 folder
  Correspondence and clippings.
- Addition (2009-0178), 2 boxes
  Accession (2009-0178) (1.2 lin. ft.; 900 items; dated 1938-1983) consists largely of Weintraub's personal correspondence to his wife, Sheila Ellen Weintraub, during World War II and his post-war travels. Other correspondents include his brother and his son. These letters offer excellent insight into Weintraub's activities during the war, as well as detailed descriptions of London and India in the pre-war and post-war period. There are also photographs and memorabilia.
  - Correspondence from London, Fall 1938 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence from London, 1939 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Correspondence and Army paperwork, May 7, 1944-Jan. 1, 1945 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Correspondence from Treasury (1942), New York City (1947), and St. Johns and Penn (1949-1951) (Box 26)
  - Correspondence from England, 1957 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1971 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence from London, 1963 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence from India, Fall 1964 (Box 26)
  - Photographs, 1940-1945, 1950s, undated (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1930s-1940s (Box 26)
    Passport, UK registration, baseball scrapbook, photographs.
  - Harold Weintraub materials, 1950s (Box 26)
  - Sidney Weintraub tax returns, 1946-1967 (Box 26)
  - Obituaries and condolences, 1983 (Box 26)
- Oversize Material, 1 folder
  - Research computations and graphs as well as awards from various institutions (Box Sec. A OV5)